Guide to the Ernie O'Malley Papers AIA.060
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II. Correspondence: Incoming, 1922-1956
  - Rothenstein, John (Director, Tate Gallery) also letter from Geroge Nicholson, 1945-1946; cuid36672 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Ryan, Desmond (author), Dec 14, 1936; cuid36673 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Saenz, Moises (Juanita de la Beneficiencia Publica; former Mexican Minister of Education), 1931; cuid36674 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Salkeld, Cecil and Mrs. (artist), 1945, 1947; cuid36675 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Schwartz, Anne Powers (novelist), 1947-1948; cuid36676 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Sheehy, Michael (Offaly comrade), Jun 21, 1953; cuid36677 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Sheehy-Skeffington, Hanna, 1936; cuid36678 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Sommerville-Largo, Sammy, 1945; cuid36679 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Stack, Austin, 1924; cuid36680 (Box 4, Folder 85A)
  - Stevenson, Philip "Ted" (author, critic, and screenwriter; Yaddo), 1932; cuid36681 (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Stewart, Dorothy Hewkick (artist), 1930-1938; cuid36682 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Strand, Paul (photographer and film maker), 1932-1956; cuid36683 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Stuart, Stan (Limerick comrade), Nov 2, 1944; cuid36684 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Sweeny, James Johnson (curator and director at MoMA, Guggenheim, and Houston Museum of Fine Arts), 1947-1948; cuid36685 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Sweeney, John "Jack" (critic, poet, and Director of Lamon Library Poetry Room at Harvard University), 1947-1948; cuid36686 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Sykes, Gerald (Yaddo), 1932; cuid36687 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Tobin, Eva and Marion (includes photograph of "Eva and Mae Tobin", 1924, 1951, undated; cuid36688 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Traynor, Oscar (Dublin comrade), Mar 12, 1936; cuid36689 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Treacy, Jeremiah, Jan 23, 1956; cuid36690 (Box 4, Folder 94A)
  - Varney, John, 1933; cuid36691 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Villard, Marquita, circa 1933-1935; cuid36692 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Vorse, Mary Ellen Heaton (journalist; Yaddo), 1932, undated; cuid36693 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Waddington, Victor (art gallery owner), 1945; cuid36694 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Walsh, Roisin (Librarian, Dublin), Oct 14, 1936; cuid36695 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Walston, Harry and Catherine (Bob); son William, 1946-1950; cuid36696 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    This correspondence consists of 64 pages.
  - Weeks, Edward (Atlantic Monthly), 1935; cuid36697 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Weston, Edward (photographer), 1931; cuid36698 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Wilson, Thomas J. (Harvard University Press), 1947; cuid36699 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Woods, Robert and Peggy, 1947-1948; cuid36700 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Woods, Tony (Hospitals' Trust), 1936-1954, undated; cuid36701 (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Young, Ella (mystic, poet), 1930; cuid36702 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Zablodowsky, David (Viking Press), 1935; cuid36703 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - [Unknown] (Carroll of Chicago), 1934; cuid36704 (Box 4, Folder 108)
    This correspondence consists of 11 pages.
  - Various: Christmas Cards, circa 1936-1955; cuid36705 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Various: Postcards, 1927-1951; cuid36706 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    This correspondence consists of 26 pages.
  - [Unknown] (Ranchi Ottorino D., Counsel to Mrs. Ranchi), 1929; cuid36707 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - [Unknown], 1955; cuid36708 (Box 4, Folder 111A)
  - [Unknown] (London), 1956; cuid36709 (Box 4, Folder 111B)
  - [Unknown] ("Kae"), 1933; cuid36710 (Box 4, Folder 111C)
- Series III. Correspondence: Outgoing, 1922-1956
  Letters from Ernie O'Malley to friends, associates, artists, editors, professors, military comrades, government agencies, solicitors, and other correspondents in Ireland and the United States between the years of 1922 and 1956. Topics in this series range broadly from general greetings to business dealings. Many of the letters provide insight into O'Malley's ailments and failing health resulting from injuries he sustained during his military career. Of special interest are letters O'Malley wrote concerning his work with the Irish Press in the United States and the status of his pension from the Irish government, as well as, transcriptions of letters from O'Malley to Monsignor John Hagan with O'Malley using the alias, Cecil Smyth-Howard, during his European travels in 1925 and 1926. A substantial number of items in this series are photocopies received from various universities and institutions, at the request of Cormac O'Malley, Ernie O'Malley's youngest son. Throughout the course of research on his father Cormac O'Malley also transcribed a considerable number of the letters written by Ernie O'Malley. Those transcriptions have been included with the original or photocopy when available. See accompanying index for a complete listing of correspondents indicating where originals are currently held, as well as, the volume of correspondence associated with each correspondent.
  - Index to Correspondence: Outgoing, 2010; cuid36711 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Aiken, Frank, 1928-1932; cuid36712 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Ames, Elizabeth (Yaddo), 1932; cuid36713 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Beaslia, Piaras, 1953; cuid36714 (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Brady, Jim, Jan 30, 1949; cuid36715 (Box 4, Folder 115A)
  - Brady, Kathleen (Kay), 1925-1926; cuid36716 (Box 4, Folder 116)
    This correspondence consists of 43 pages.
  - Brennan, Maurteen (Martin), 1951; cuid36717 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Brett, Dorothy, 1930; cuid36718 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - British and Irish Steam Packet Co., 1938; cuid36719 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine Childers), 1923-1924; cuid36720 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    This correspondence consists of 60 pages.
  - Childers, Mary Alden Osgood (Mrs. Erskine Childers) (see also Subject Files), 1923; cuid36721 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    This correspondence consists of 63 pages.
  - Citkowitz-Liber, Rebecca, 1952; cuid36722 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Clifford-Comer, Madge (Mrs. Jack Comer), 1924-1937; cuid36723 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Comer, Ellis, Dec 30, 1937; cuid36724 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Davis, Chester C. (Simpson, Thatcher and Barlett; re expenses for EOM/COM), 1955-1956; cuid36725 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    This correspondence consists of 33 pages.
  - Department of Defence, Mar 1, 1954; cuid36726 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - DeValera, Eamon, 1931; cuid36727 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Feehan, Matt, Oct 1955; cuid36728 (Box 4, Folder 127A)
  - Fitzgerald, Mabel (from jail), 1921-1924; cuid36729 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Ford, John, 1953; cuid36730 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Gallagher, Frank, 1926-1954 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Gaynor, Sean, Sep 1955; cuid36731 (Box 5, Folder 1A)
  - Gilchrist, Thomas B., 1947-1950; cuid36732 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Golden, Helen Merriam, 1930-1935; cuid36733 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    This correspondence consists of 58 pages.
  - Golden-Sax, Eithne, 1934-1955; cuid36734 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    This correspondence consists of 57 pages.
  - Hagan, Monsignor John, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Herbert, Robert (Librarian, Co. Limerick), 1942-1956; cuid36735 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hughes, Mary (envelope only), undated; cuid36736 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Humphreys, Sigle (Sheila, Mrs. Donal O'Donoghue), 1922-1931 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Irish Estates (EOM's Irish apartment landlord), Jul 2, 1955; cuid36737 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Irish Land Commission, May 23, 1942; cuid36738 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Irish Pension Board, 1934-1950; cuid36739 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    This correspondence consists of 22 pages.
  - Kelleher, John V., 1947-1950 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Kelly, [P.J.], Westport, 1945; cuid36740 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Kerrigan, Georgette, (Donegal), 1951; cuid36741 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - MacGreevy, Thomas, 1939-1940, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Manahan, Liam, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - McDonnell, Capt. P.J., 1956; cuid36742 (Box 5, Folder 16A)
  - McGrail, Jean (America sculptor, travel writer), 1955-1956; cuid36743 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    This correspondence consists of 111 pages.
  - McHugh, Patricia "Patsy" (Mrs. Roger McHugh), Sep 22, 1955; cuid36744 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - McHugh, Roger, Apr 23, 1945; cuid36745 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - McManus, Francis (Radio Eireann), 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Military Pension Board, Oct 1938-May 1950; cuid36746 (Box 5, Folder 20A)
  - Monroe, Harriet (Poetry Magazine), 1934-1935; cuid36747 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Murphy, Maigread, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Nolan, Dan (The Kerryman), Oct 31, 1952; cuid36748 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Noyk, Michael, Esq (attorney for Ernie O'Malley), 1950-1953, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - O'Donovan, James (transcripts of letters), 1936 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - O'Dowd, John, Jul 19, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - O'Rahilly, Aodogan and Maureen, Dec 1937 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - O'Reilly, Tom, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - O'Sullivan, Seamus, 1947, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Plunkett, Countess (Mary Josephine), 1923, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Power, George (Cork military interview), Dec 19, 1951; cuid36749 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Raleigh, John, 1925-1955, undated; cuid36750 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    This correspondence consists of 40 pages.
  - Raleigh, Peggy, 1938; cuid36751 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Rothenstein, John (Tate Gallery, London), Oct 26, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Ryan, Desmond, 1936, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Sheehy, Michael, 1951-1956 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Solomons, Estella, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Somerville-Large, Mrs. Sammy, May 6, 1950; cuid36752 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Stephenson, Dan, circa 9153; cuid36753 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Strand, Paul (papers from Center for Creative Photography Archives, Unversity of Arizona), 1932, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Sunday Press, 1955-1596 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Sweeney, James Johnson and Laura, 1939-1955; cuid36754 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    This correspondence consists of 27 pages.
  - Wall, Mervyn (Radio Eireann), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Weston, Edward (papers from Center for Creative Photography Archives, Unversity of Arizona), 1929, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Series IV. Correspondence: Family, 1914-1957
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence between Ernie O'Malley and members of his family including his mother, siblings, children, wife, in-laws, cousins and others. Also included in this series are letters from family members that were neither addressed to nor written by O'Malley. As in other Correspondence Series, numerous photocopies of originals exist within this series. See index for a complete listing.
  - Index to Correspondence: Family, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Burton, Gertrude Kearney, circa 1915-1916 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Hooker, Blanche Ferry (mother-in-law), 1938-1948; cuid36755 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Hooker, Elon Huntington (father-in-law), 1935-1937; cuid36756 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Laithwaite, Sylvia (Ernie O'Malley's first cousin; interesting background on O'Malley), 1930-1945; cuid36757 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Malley, Albert (brother), 1915; cuid36758 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Malley, Cecil and Margaret (brother and sister-in-law), 1943; cuid36759 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Malley, Kathleen (sister), 1935-1942; cuid36760 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Malley, Kevin (brother), 1930-1957; cuid36761 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Malley, Marion (mother, Mrs. Luke Malley), 1922-1946; cuid36762 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - O'Malley, Maura (Mrs. Desmond O'Malley, sister-in-law), 1945-1948; cuid36763 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Malley, Sweetie (sister, Marion), 1947-1948; cuid36764 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Marquand, Adelaide Hooker (sister-in-law), 1936, 1948; cuid36765 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - O'Malley, Cathal (son; mostly Ernie O'Malley correspondence), 1939-1957, undated; cuid36766 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    This correspondence consists of 107 pages.
  - O'Malley, Cathal (son): Diary, 1946; cuid36854 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    This correspondence consists of 122 pages.
  - O'Malley, Cormac (son), 1948-1953, undated; cuid36767 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - O'Malley, Ernie to Helen, Cathal, Etain I (copies), 1942-1955 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - O'Malley, Ernie to Helen, Cathal, Etain II (copies), 1942-1955 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - O'Malley, Etain (daughter), 1945-1956, undated; cuid36768 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    This correspondence consists of 49 pages.
  - O'Malley, Helen Hooker, 1937-1955; cuid36769 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    This correspondence consists of 180 pages.
  - O'Malley, Helen Hooker: I (copies), 1933-1939 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - O'Malley, Helen Hooker: II (copies), 1933-1939 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Transcriptions of select family correspondence 1933-1956 by Cormac O'Malley, 1933-1956, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 67)
- Series V. Personal, 1912-2006
  Series is arranged alphabetically by type, generally.
  Address books, memberships, book slips, inventories, lists, invitations, announcements, school records, memorabilia and other miscellaneous materials covering various events in Ernie O'Malley's life. Throughout the course of his life O'Malley, an avid reader, acquired a vast and diverse personal library. Due to financial hardships during the late 1940s and early 1950s O'Malley was forced to sell a substantial portion of books from his personal library. Card catalogs and inventories in this series reflect the many changes in his personal collection of books before and following the sale. Of special interest is a collection of book slips from the National Library of Ireland, New York Public Library and Newberry Library in Chicago, Illinois documenting the hundreds of books O'Malley read or checked out from each institution during the 1930s.
  - Index to Personal, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 1A)
  - Address Book: United States, 1928 (Box 42, Folder 28)
  - Address Books, 1944-1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Address Books, 1950-1955 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Address Book, 1953 (Box 42, Folder 29)
  - Catlogue of Printed Books: Southeby & Company, London (2 copies), 1949 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Ernie O'Malley and Helen Hungtington Hooker - scrapbook of articles by and about, Dec 2006 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Funeral Photographs, Mar 1957 (Box 6, Folder 4A)
  - Inventories of Books, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Inventories of Books - typed and annotated, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Inventories of Books: Missing books, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Inventory of Books: Card catalog slips (inventory of O'Malley book collection) and handwritten Spanish flashcards (5-8 in inventory), undated (Box 30)
  - Inventory of Books: Card catalog slips (inventory of O'Malley book collection) and handwritten Spanish flashcards (5-8 in inventory), undated (Box 31)
  - Inventory of Books: Book slips, circa 1932-1940 (Box 32)
    Book slips from the National Library of Ireland covering books EOM was reading on Irish history, literature, drama, poetry, archaeology, early Irish Christian Ireland, European Renaissance art, art generally, military history, geography; slips from the New York Public Library covering books EOM was reading on Irish literature (James, William Butler Yeats, Lady Gregory, P Column, etc); history book slips from the Newberry Library in Chicago, Illinois coverning books EOM was reading while working at the World's Fair on Irish/Welsh (Items 5-5, 5-6 5-7)
  - Inventories of Paintings from Personal Collection, circa 1947 (Box 6, Folder 7A)
  - Irish Academy of Letters, circa 1946, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Irish Ration Book, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Membership Cards: Sinn Fein (Ernie O'Malley); English Speaking Union Club (Mrs. Ernie O'Malley), 1925, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Nameplate - hand colored (Ernie O'Malley), undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Notes: French literature bibliography on index cards, circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 11A)
  - Passport [false], 1925 (Box 6, Folder 11B)
  - Photographs: General, 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 11C)
  - Postcards, undated (Box 6, Folder 11D)
  - Reading List for [O'Malley] Children, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Results - Annual Examination (Ernie O'Malley): O'Connell School, Dublin, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Schedule during stay with Golden Family in New Mexico, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Series VI. Legal, 1921-1957
  The series contains legal documents and clippings relating to Ernie O'Malley between the years of 1923 and 1957. Most materials in this series relate to the legal proceedings between O'Malley and his estranged wife, Helen Hooker O'Malley in 1950. Also included are clippings documenting the libel lawsuit and settlement between Joseph O'Doherty and Ernie O'Malley following O'Malley's publication of On Another Man's Wound. Many of the official legal documents in this series are photocopies received from the High Court of Justice in Dublin, Ireland.
  - Index to Legal, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 15A)
  - Affidavit: O'Malley Helen Hooker v. O'Malley, Ernest, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Boat Registration "Brendan Naomha" (St. Brendan), 1946 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Certificates: Birth and Death: May 27, 1897, March 25, 1957 (copies made in 1993), 1897, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Contract, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 17A)
  - Drivers License (paperwork), 1937, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Gun Permit, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Legal Brief - Abstract of Evidence in the case of Ernie O'Malley, civilian present in Military Custody, Jan 11, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Libel Action: Joe O'Doherty (regarding On Another Man's Wound) original clippings, 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Libel Action: Joe O'Doherty (regarding On Another Man's Wound) clippings (copies), 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Marriage Certificate (copy), Sept 27, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - O'Malley v. O'Malley: Judgment (Dismissal), Mar 30, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - O'Malley v. O'Malley: Summons, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Will (signed copy), Marh 1957 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Series VII. Financial, 1935-1957
  This series contains invoices, receipts, bills and correspondence from purveyors and businesses pertaining to items bought for the O'Malley household, including food, clothing, electricity, household furnishings, car repairs and books and publications. The material provides a unique and intimate look into the personal life of the O'Malley family.
  - Index to Financial, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 27A)
  - Cancelled Checks, Check Registers, and Check Stubs, 1949-1955 (Box 43)
  - Check Registers, 1949-1955 (Box 42, Folder 45-47)
  - Farm Expenses, 1940-1946 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Hibernian Bank Ltd., Account Book and cover (oversize), 1940-1957 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I (furnishings, groceries, etc.), 1936 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Household Expenses: Bills, Invoices, Receipts, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts (with copies), 1938 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts (with copies), 1939 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts (with copies), 1940 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts II, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts II, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts I, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts II, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Household Expenses: Bills and Receipts, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Income Tax Records, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personal Expenses Ledger (Ernie O'Malley), 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Pension Papers, 1934-1953 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Real Estate: Carrowkeel land receipt and payment schedule, 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate: Map of Burrishoole Lands, circa 1941-1945 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Series VIII. Nationalistic Material, 1643-1966, undated
  Materials in this series are in two groups: military training manuals, arranged chronologically, and printed material, arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains newspaper clippings, booklets, notes, pamphlets, military training manuals, reports, memorandums, photographs and other printed matter relating to the nationalist movement in Ireland. Drawn to the nationalist cause in midst of the Easter Rising in 1916, O'Malley later joined the Irish Republican Army and became a key figure in the War of Independence and Irish Civil War. Items in this series provide details of O'Malley's military career, as well as, insight into the publications and propaganda that powered the nationalist movement throughout Ireland. Also included in this series are official reports and memoranda issued by Oglaigh na hEireann, otherwise known as the Irish Republican Army. Of special interest in this series are a few items relating to O'Malley's interviews with veterans of the War of Independence and Civil War. Beginning in the early 1940s, O'Malley embarked on an ambitious effort to document first-hand accounts of both wars and as a result, hand-recorded approximately 450 interviews with his former military comrades. Most items relating to his military interviews were placed in the archives of University College Dublin in 1974, however, a limited amount of materials pertaining to the interviews remain in this series.
  - Index to Nationalistic material, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Military Training Manual: Field Service Pocketbook,1914 with 1916 amendments (signed) (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry Consisting of Theory of Rifle Fire 1. Elementary; 2. Advance (Forster Groom and Co., Ltd., London), 1916-1919 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Military Training Manual: Notes on Elementary Field Training Part II (publisher: Hugh Rees Ltd., London), 1915 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry Consisting of Aiming Instruction and Firing Instruction by Simplex (Forster, Groom and Co., Ltd., London), 1916 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry Consisting of Visual Training and Judging Distance (Forster Groom and Co., Ltd., London), 1916-1919 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Military Training Manual: Notes for Infantry Officers on Trench Warfare, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Military Training Manual: Artillery Map Reading and Elementary Gunnery Made Easy by "Gunlayer" and "Contour" (Gale and Polden, Ltd., London), 1918-1921 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Military Training Manual: Lewis Gun Training, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Military Training Manual: Musketry '303 and '22 Cartridges, Elementary Training, Visual Training, etc. (John Murray, London), 1922 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Military Training Manual: Bayonet Fighting for War by Captain Leopold McLaglen (Harrison and Sons, London), undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Military Training Manual: Oglaig na hEireann "Cyclist Training Manual, Handbook No. 7" (IRA Official Publications), undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Photographs: Liam Lynch, IRA Chief of Staff; Dublin Castle, circa 1936, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - An tOglac: Offical organ of the Irish Volunteers Vol. 1, nos. 2 and 3, Sep 1918 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - The Constitution of the Free State of Ireland 1921 English translation (Stationery Office of Dublin), undate (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - "The Countermanding Orders of Holy Week, 1916" by Diarmuid Lynch in An Cosantoir, Dublin, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Dial Eireann: Official correspondence relating to the peace negotiations, June-September 1921, Oct 1921 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - "The Drama of Eight Days June 22-29, 1922: How War Was Waged on Ireland with an Economy of English Lives," American Association for the Recognition of the Irish Republic (Box 7, Folder 29)